mutton.
Up jumped Bilbo, and putting on his dressing gown, went into the dining
room. There he saw nobody, but all the signs of a large and hurried breakfast.
There was a fearful mess in the room, and piles of unwashed crocs in the
kitchen. Nearly every pot and pan he possessed seemed to have been used. The
washing up was so dismally real that Bilbo was forced to believe the party of
the night before had not been part of his bad dreams, as he had rather hoped.
Indeed, he was really relieved, after all, to think that they had all gone
without him, and without bothering to wake him up, but with never a thank you,
he thought pry them yet, in a way he could not help feeling just a trifled disappointed.
The feeling surprised him. "Don't be a fool, Belbo Baggins," he said to
himself, thinking of dragons and all that outlandish nonsense at your age. So
he put on an apron, lit fires, boiled water, and washed up. Then he had a nice
little breakfast in the kitchen before turning out the dining room. By that
time, the sun was shining, and the front door was open, letting in a warm spring
breeze. Bilbo began to whistle loudly, and to forget about the night before. In
fact, he was just sitting down to a nice little second breakfast in the dining
room by the open window when in walked Gandalf.
My dear fellow, said he, whatever are you going to come? What about an early
start, and here you are having breakfast, or whatever you call it, at 10.
They left you the message because they could not wait. What message? said poor
Mr. Baggins, all in a fluster.
Great elephants, said Gandalf. You are not at all yourself this morning. You
have never dusted the mantlepiece.
What's that got to do with it? I have had enough to do with washing up a 14.
If you had dusted the mantlepiece, you would have found this just under the
clock, said Gandalf, handing Bilbo a note written, of course, on his own note
paper. This is what he read. Thoren and company to burglar Bilbo greeting. Tia
your hospitality our sincerest thanks and for your offer of professional
assistance our grateful acceptance.
Terms cash on delivery up to and not exceeding 1/14th of total profits if
any. All traveling expenses guaranteed in any event. funeral expenses to be
defraed by us or our representatives if occasion arises and the matter is not
otherwise arranged for. Thinking it unnecessary to disturb your esteemed
repose, we have proceeded in advance to make requisite preparations and shall
await your respected person at the Green Dragon Inn by water at 11:00 a.m. sharp,
trusting that you will be punctual.
We have the honor to remain yours deeply, Thoren and Co. That leaves you
just 10 minutes. You will have to run, said Gandalf.
But said Bilbo. No time for it, said the wizard. But said Bilbo again. No time
for that either. Off he go. to the end of his days. Bilbo could never remember
how he found himself outside without a hat, a walking stick, or any money, or
anything that he usually took when he went out, leaving his second breakfast
half-finish and quite unwashed up, pushing his keys into Gandalf's hands,
and running as fast as his furry feet could carry him down the lane, past the
great mill, across the water, and then on for a mile or more. Barry puffed he
was when he got to buy water just on the stroke of 11 and found he had come
without a pocket handkerchief. "Bravo," said Balin, who was standing at the
indoor looking out for him. Just then all the others came round the corner of
the road from the village. They were on ponies, and each pony was slung about
with all kinds of baggages, packages, parcels, and paraphernelia. There was a
very small pony, apparently for Bilbo.
Up you two get and off we go, said Thoren.
I'm awfully sorry, said Bobo, but I have come without my hat, and I have left my
pocket handkerchief behind, and I haven't got any money. I didn't get your
note until after 10:45 to be precise.
Don't be precise, said Dallan. And don't worry, you will have to manage without
pocket handkerchiefs and a good many other things before you get to the
journeys end. As for a hat, I have got a spare hood and cloak in my luggage.
That's how they all came to start, jogging off from the inn one fine
morning just before May on laden ponies, and Bilbo was wearing a dark green hood,
a little weather stained, and a dark green cloak borrowed from Dwallan. They
were too large for him, and he looked rather comic. What his father, Bungo,
would have thought of him, I dare think.
His only comfort was he couldn't be mistaken for a dwarf as he had no beard.
They had not been riding very long when up came Gandalf very splendid on a white
horse. He had brought a lot of pocket handkerchiefs and Bilbo's pipe and
tobacco. So after that the party went along very merrily, and they told
stories or sang songs as they rode forward all day, except of course when
they stopped for meals. These didn't come quite as often as Bilbo would have
liked them, but still he began to feel that adventures were not so bad after
all. At first they had passed through Hobbit lands, a wide, respectable
country inhabited by decent folk with good roads, an inn or two, and now and
then a door for a farmer amling by on business. Then they came to lands where
people spoke strangely and sang songs Bilbo had never heard before. Now they
had gone on far into the lone lands where there were no people left, no ins,
and the roads grew steadily worse. Not far ahead were dreary hills rising
higher and higher, dark with trees. On some of them were old castles with an
evil look, as if they have been built by wicked people. Everything seemed gloomy,
for the weather that day had taken a nasty turn. Mostly it had been as good
as May can be, can be, even in Merry Tales, but now it was cold and wet. In
the Lone Lands they had been obliged to camp when they could, but at least it
had been dry. To think it will soon be June, grumbled Bilbo, as he splashed
along behind the others in a very muddy track. It was after tea time. It was
pouring with rain and had been all day.
His hood was dripping into his eyes. His cloak was full of water. The pony was
tired and stumbled on stones. The others were too grumpy to talk. And I'm sure
the rain has got into the dry clothes and into the food bags, thought Bilbo.
Father Burgling and everything to do with it. I wish I was at home in my nice
hall by the fire, with the cattle just beginning to sing. It was not the last
time that he wished that. Still the doors joged on, never turning round or
taking any notice of the hobbit.
Somewhere behind the gray clouds the sun must have gone down, for it began to get
dark as they went down into a deep valley with a river at the bottom. Wind
got up, and willows along its banks bent inside. Fortunately the road went over
an ancient stone bridge, for the river, swollen with the rains, came rushing
down from the hills and mountains in the north. It was nearly night when they had
crossed over. The wind broke up the gray clouds, and a wandering moon appeared
above the hills between the flying rags.
Then they stopped, and Thoren muttered something about supper. And where shall
we get a dry patch to sleep on? Not until then did they noticed that Gandalf
was missing. So far he had come all the way with them, never saying if he was in
the adventure, or merely keeping them company for a while. He had eaten most,
talked most, and laughed most, but now he simply was not there at all, just
when a wizard would have been most useful. Two, grown Dory and Nory, who
shared the hobbit's views about regular meals plenty and often, they decided in
the end that they would have to camp where they were. They moved to a clump
of trees, and though it was drier under them, the wind shook the rain off the
leaves, and the drip drip was most annoying. Also, the mischief seemed to
have got into the fire. Dwarves can make a fire almost anywhere out of almost
anything, wind or no wind, but they could not do it that night, not even Oin
and Gloin, who were specially good at it. Then one of the ponies took fright
at nothing and bolted. He got into the river before they could catch him, and
before they could get him out again, Feelely and Keely were nearly drowned,
and all the baggage that he carried was washed away off him. Of course, it was
mostly food, and there was mighty little left for supper, and less for breakfast.
There they all sat glum and wet, and muttering, while Oin and Gloin went on
trying to light the fire, and quarreling about it. Bilbo was sadly reflecting
that adventures are not all pony rides in May sunshine when Balon, who was
always their lookout man, said, "There is a light over there. There was a hill
some way off with trees on it, pretty thick in parts." Out of the dark mass of
the trees, they could now see a light shining, a reddish, comfortable looking
light, as it might be a fire or torches twinkling. When they had looked at it
for some while, they fell to arguing.
Some said no, and some said yes. Some said they could but go and see, and
anything was better than little supper, less breakfast, and wet clothes all the
night. Others said, "These parts are none too wellknown, and are too near the
mountains. Travelers seldom come this way now. The old maps are no use. Things
have changed for the worse, and the road is unguarded. They have seldom even
heard of the king round here, and the less inquisitive you are as you go
along, the less trouble you are likely to find. Some said, "After all, there
are 14 of us." Others said, "Where has Gandalf got to?" This remark was
repeated by everybody. Then the rain began to pour down worse than ever, and
Oin and Gloin began to fight. "That settled it. After all, we have got a
burglar with us," they said. And so they made off, leading their ponies, with all
due and proper caution in the direction of the light. They came to the hill and
were soon in the wood. Up the hill they went, but there was no proper path to be
seen, such as might lead to a house or a farm, and do what they could. They made
a deal of rustling and crackling and creaking, and a good deal of grumbling
and drading as they went through the trees in the pitch dark. Suddenly the
red light shone out very bright through the tree trunks not far ahead. Now it is
the burglar's turn, they said, meaning Bilbo. You must go on and find out all
about that light and what it is for, and if all is perfectly safe and canny, said
Thorin to the Hobbit. Now scuttle off, and come back quick if all is well. If
not, come back if you can. If you can't hoot twice like a barn owl and once like
a screech owl, and we will do what we can. Off. Bilbo had to go before he
could explain that he could not hoot even once like any kind of owl any more
than fly like a bat. But at any rate, hobbits can move quietly in woods,
absolutely quietly. They take a pride in it, and Bilbo had sniffed more than once
at what he called all this dwarfish racket as they went along, though I
don't suppose you or I would have noticed anything at all on a windy
night. Not if the whole cavalcade had passed 2 ft off.
As for Bilbo walking primly towards the red light, I don't suppose even a weasel
would have stirred a whisker at it. So naturally, he got right up to the fire
for fire. It was without disturbing anyone. And this is what he saw. Three
very large persons sitting around a very large fire of beach logs. They were
toasting mutton on long spits of wood and licking the gravy off their fingers.
There was a fine tooth smell. Also, there was a barrel of good drink at
hand, and they were drinking out of jugs. But they were trolls, obviously
trolls. Even Bilbo, in spite of his sheltered life, could see that from the
great heavy faces of them, and their size, and the shape of their legs, not
to mention their language, which was not drawing room fashion at all, at all.
Mutton yesterday, mutton today, and blimey if it don't look like mutton
again to said one of the trolls.
Never a blinking bit of man flesh have we had for long enough, said a second.
What the L William was a think enough to bring us into these parts at all beats
me and the drink running short. What's more, he said, jogging the elbow of
William, who was taking a pull at his jug. William choked. Shut your mouth, he
said as soon as he could. You can't expect folk to stop here forever just to
be at by you and Bert. You've at a village and a half between year since we
come down from the mountains. How much more dire want? And time's been up our
way when you have said, "Thank you, Bill, for a nice bit of fat valley
mutton like what this is." He took a big bite off a sheep's leg he was roasting
and wiped his lips on his sleeve.
Yes, I am afraid trolls do behave like that, even those with only one head
each. After hearing all this, Bilbo ought to have done something at once.
Either he should have gone back quietly and warned his friends that there were
three fair-sized trolls at hand in a nasty mood, quite likely to try roasted
dwarf or even pony for a change. Or else he should have done a bit of good quick
burging. A really first class and legendary burglar would at this point
have picked the trolls pockets. It is nearly always worthwhile, if you could
manage it, pinched the very mutton off the spits, pearloined the beer, and
walked off without their noticing him.
Others, more practical, but with less professional pride, would perhaps have
stuck a dagger into each of them before they observed it. Then the night could
have been spent cheerily.
Bilbo knew it. He had read of a good many things he had never seen or done.
He was very much alarmed as well as disgusted. He wished himself a 100 miles
away, and yet and yet somehow he could not go straight back to Thoren and
company empty-handed. So he stood and hesitated in the shadows. Of the various
burglarious proceedings he had heard of, picking the trolls pockets seemed the
least difficult, so at last he crept behind a tree just behind William.
Bert and Tom went off to the barrel.
William was having another drink. Then Bilbo plucked up courage and put his
little hand in William's enormous pocket. There was a purse in it as big
as a bag to Bilbo. Fought thought he, warming to his new work as he lifted it
carefully out. This is a beginning.
It was. Trolls purses are the mischief, and this was no exception. air. Oh, are
you? It squeaked as it left the pocket, and William turned round at once and
grabbed Bilbo by the neck before he could duck behind the tree. Blimey Bert,
look what I've coped, said William. What is it? said the others coming up. Lummy,
if I knows, what are you? Bilbo Baggins, a bur hobbit, said poor Bilbo, shaking
all over and wondering how to make owl noises before they throttled him. A bur
hobbit? said they, a bit startled.
Trolls are slow in the uptake, and mighty suspicious about anything new to
them. What's a bur hobbit got to do with my pocket anyways? said William. And can
you cook them? said Tom. You can try, said Bert, picking up a skewer. He
wouldn't make above a mouthful, said William, who had already had a fine
supper, not when he was skinned and boned. Perhaps there are more like him
round about, and we might make a pie, said Bert. Here you are there any more
of your sort, as Nikon and these here woods, your nasty little rabbit? Said
he, looking at the hobbit's furry feet, and he picked him up by the toes and
shook him. Yes, lots, said Bilbo before he remembered not to give his friends
away. No, none. None at all, not one, he said immediately afterwards.
What dire mean, said Bert, holding him right way up by the hair this time. What
I say, said Bil, gasping. And please don't cook me, kind sir. I am a good
cook myself, and cook better than I cook, if you see what I mean. I'll cook
beautifully for you, a perfectly beautiful breakfast for you. If only you
won't have me for supper.
Poor little Blider, said William. He had already had as much supper as he could
hold. Also, he had had lots of beer.
Poor little Blider. Let him go. Not till he says what he means by lots and none
at all, said Bird. I don't want to have me throw cut in me sleep. Hold his toes
in the fire till he talks.
I won't have it, said William. I caught him anyway. You're a fat fool, William,
said Bert, as I've said before this evening. And you're a lout. And I won't
take that from you, Bill Huggin, says Bert, and put his fist in William's eye.
Then there was a gorgeous row. Bilbo had just enough wits left when Boat dropped
him on the ground to scramble out of the way of their feet before they were
fighting like dogs and calling one another all sorts of perfectly true and
applicable names in very loud voices.
Soon they were locked in one another's arms and rolling nearly into the fire,
kicking and thumping, while Tom whacked at them both with a branch to bring them
to their senses, and that of course only made them matter than ever. That would
have been the time for Bilbo to have left. But his poor little feet had been
very squashed in Bert's big paw, and he had no breath in his body, and his head
was going round. So there he lay for a while, panting, just outside the circle
of fire light. Right in the middle of the fight, up came Balum. The dwarves
had heard noises from a distance and after waiting for some time for Bilbo to
come back or to hoot like an owl. They started off one by one to creep towards
the light as quietly as they could. No sooner did Tom see Balon come into the
light than he gave an awful howl. Trolls simply detest the very sight of dwarves
uncooked. Bert and Bill stop fighting immediately and a sack Tom. Quick, they
said before Balon, who was wondering where in all this commotion Bilbo was,
knew what was happening, a sack was over his head, and he was down. "There's more
to come yet," said Tom. "Or I mighty mistook. Lots and none at all." "It is,"
said he. "No Bits, but lots of these here dwarves. That's about the shape of
it." "I reckon you're right," said Bert, "and we best get out of the light." And
so they did. With sacks in their hands that they used for carrying off mutton
and other plunder, they waited in the shadows. As each dwarf came up and
looked at the fire, and the spilled jugs and the nod mutton in surprise pop, went
a nasty smelly sack over his head, and he was down. Soon Dwellin lay by Balin
and Fely and Keely together and Dory and Nori and Aie all in a heap and Oin and
Gloin and Bour and Buffer and Bombor piled uncomfortably near the fire.
That'll teach him, said Tom, for Bifur and Bomber had given a lot of trouble
and fought like mad as dwarves will when cornered. Thoren came last, and he was
not caught unawares. He came expecting mischief and didn't need to see his
friend's legs sticking out of sacks to tell him that things were not all well.
He stood outside in the shadows some way off and said, "What's all this trouble?
Who has been knocking my people about "It's trolls," said Bilbo from behind a
tree. "They had forgotten all about him.
They're hiding in the bushes with sacks," said he. "Oh, are they?" said
Thoren, and he jumped forward to the fire before they could leap on him. He
caught up a big branch all on fire at
one end, and Bo got that end in his eye before he could step aside. That put him
out of the battle for a bit. Bilbo did his best. He caught hold of Tom's leg as
well as he could. It was thick as a young tree trunk, but he was sent
spinning up into the top of some bushes when Tom kicked the sparks up in Thoren's face.
the trolls. Tom got the branch in his teeth for that and lost one of the front
ones. It made him howl, I can tell you.
But just at that moment, William came up behind and popped a sack right over
Thoren's head and down to his toes. And so the fight ended. A nice pickle they
were all in now, all neatly tied up in sacks, with three angry trolls, and two
with burns and bashes to remember.
sitting by them arguing whether they should roast them slowly or mince them
fine and boil them or just sit on them one by one and squash them into jelly.
And Bilbo up in a bush with his clothes and his skin torn, not daring to move
for fear they should hear him. It was just then that Gandalf came back, but no
one saw him. The trolls had just decided to roast the dwarves now and eat them
later. That was Bert's idea, and after a lot of argument, they had all agreed to
it. "No good roasting them now. It' take all night," said a voice. Bert thought
it was Williams. "Don't start the argument all over again, Bill," he said.
"Or it will take all night." "Who's arguing?" said William, "Who thought it
was Bert that had spoken?" "You are," said Bert. "You're a liar," said
William. And so the argument began all over again. In the end they decided to
mince them fine and boil them. So they got a great black pot and they took out
their knives.
No good boiling them. We ain't got no water and it's a long way to the well
and all said a voice. B and William thought it was Tom's.
Shut up said they or will never have done and you can fetch the water
yourself if you say anymore.
Shut up yourself, said Tom, who thought it was William's voice. Who's arguing
but you? I'd like to know. You're a booby, said William. Booby yourself,
said Tom. And so the argument began all over again, and went on harder than
ever, until at last they decided to sit on the sacks one by one, and squash
them, and boil them next time. "Who shall we sit on first?" said the voice.
Better sit on the last fellow first, said Bert, whose eye had been damaged by
Thorin. He thought Tom was talking.
Don't talk to yourself, said Tom. But if he wants to sit on the last one, sit on
him. Which is he? The one with the yellow stockings, said Bird. Nonsense.
The one with the gray stockings, said a voice like Williams. I made sure it was
yellow, said Bird. Yellow it was, said William. Then what did you say it was
gray for? said Bert. I never did, Tom said. It I never did, said Tom. It was
you. Two to one. So shut your mouth, said Bert. Who are you are talking to?
said William. Now stop it, said Tom and Bert together. The night's getting on
and Don comes early. Let's get on with it. Dawn take you all and be stoned to
you," said a voice that sounded like Williams. But it wasn't, for just at
that moment the light came over the hill, and there was a mighty twitter in
the branches. William never spoke, for he stood turned to stone as he stooped,
and Boat and Tom were stuck like rocks as they looked at him, and there they
stand to this day, all alone, unless the birds perch on them. For trolls, as you
probably know, must be underground before dawn, or they go back to the
stuff of the mountains they are made of, and never move again. That is what had
happened to Bo and Tom and William.
Excellent, said Gandalf, as he stepped from behind a tree and helped Bilbo to
climb down out of a thorn bush. Then Bilbo understood. It was the wizard's
voice that had kept the trolls bickering and quarreling until the light came and
made an end of them. The next thing was to untie the sacks and let out the
dorbs. They were nearly suffocated and very annoyed. They had not at all
enjoyed lying there listening to the trolls making plans for roasting them
and squashing them and mincing them.
They had to hear Bilbo's account of what had happened to him twice over before
they were satisfied.
Silly time to go practicing pinching and pocket picking, said Bomber, when what
we wanted was fire and food. And that's just what you wouldn't have got of those
fellows without a struggle. In any case, said Gandalf.
Anyhow, you are wasting time now. Don't you realize that the trolls must have a
cave or a hole dug somewhere near to hide from the sun in? We must look into
it. They searched about and soon found the marks of trolls stony boots going
away through the trees. They followed the tracks up the hill until hidden by
bushes they came on a big door of stone leading to a cave. But they could not
open it, not though they all pushed while Gandalf tried various incantations.
"Would this be any good?" asked Belbo when they were getting tired and angry.
"I found it on the ground where the trolls had their fight. He held out a
largestish key, though no doubt William had thought it very small and secret. It
must have fallen out of his pocket very luckily before he was turned to stone.
"Why didn't you mention it before?" they cried. Gandalf grabbed it and fitted it
into the keyhole. Then the stone door swung back with one big push, and they
all went inside. There were bones on the floor, and a nasty smell was in the air.
But there was a good deal of food jumbled carelessly on shelves and on the
[clears throat] ground, among an untidy litter of plunder, of all sorts, from
brass buttons to pots full of gold coins standing in a corner. There were lots of
clothes, too, hanging on the walls, too small for trolls. I am afraid they
belong to victims, and among them were several swords of various makes, shapes,
and sizes. Two caught their eyes, particularly because of their beautiful
scabbards and jeweled hilts. Gandalf and Thor and each took one of these, and
Bilbo took a knife in a leather sheath.
It would have made only a tiny pocket knife for a troll, but it was as good as
a short sword for the hobbit. "These look like good blades," said the wizard,
half-drawing them and looking at them curiously.
They were not made by any troll, nor by any smith among men in these parts and
days. But when we can read the runes on them, we shall know more about them.
Let's get out of this horrible smell, said Feelely. So they carried out the
parts of coins, and such food as was untouched, and looked fit to eat, also
one barrel of ale, which was still full.
By that time they felt like breakfast, and being very hungry, they did not turn
their noses up at what they had got from the trolls lauder. Their own provisions
were very scanty. Now they had bread and cheese and plenty of ale and bacon to
toast in the embers of the fire. After that they slept, for their night had
been disturbed, and they did nothing more till the afternoon. Then they
brought up their ponies and carried away the pots of gold and buried them very
secretly not far from the track by the river, putting a great many spells over
them, just in case they ever had the chance to come back and recover them.
When that was done, they all mounted once more and joged along again on the
path towards the east. "Where did you go to, if I may ask?" said Thoren to
Gandalf as they rode along. To look ahead, said he. And what brought you
back in the nick of time? Looking behind, said he. Exactly, said Thoren.
But could you be more plain? I went on to spy out our road. It will soon become
dangerous and difficult. Also, I was anxious about replenishing our small
stock of provisions. I had not gone very far, however, when I met a couple of
friends of mine from Riendell.
Where's that? asked Bilbo. Don't interrupt, said Gandalf. You will get
there in a few days now, if we're lucky, and find out all about it. As I was
saying, I met two of Elron's people.
They were hurrying along for fear of the trolls. It was they who told me that
three of them had come down from the mountains and settled in the woods, not
far from the road. They had frightened everyone away from the district and they
waylaid strangers.
I immediately had a feeling that I was wanted back. Looking behind, I saw a
fire in the distance and made for it. So now you know. Please be more careful.
Next time or we shall never get anywhere.
Thank you, said Doran. Chapter 3. A